[SPEAKER_03]: You know, it's that... No, like, especially in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, when you actually start developing the concept of celibacy or the idea that this is what you should be striving at.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, you know, there comes a point the whole world will feel upside down when it comes to that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you know, any confidence that you build and whatever else, it just completely gets undone.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, yeah, one look at it, one eye contact, it's enough to, like, crack you, to completely overwhelm you.
[SPEAKER_03]: For a good... well, in the beginning, at least, it will boil down to enduring it, not pursuing it in any way, and also not pursuing it physically, not looking for the loopholes, and then, as the suttas would often say, seeing the danger in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that means, like, if you... like, if you have an attitude
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not necessarily pursuing any loopholes that you might find.
[SPEAKER_03]: That attitude is already an unwholesome state of looking for a loophole.
[SPEAKER_03]: It means, ah, you're not seeing the danger in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_03]: It means you're looking for a letter of the rule to keep you from breaking it or to allow you a loophole.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, actually, you should look for the origin of such action, which is your own mind, which is whether it's rooted in wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you're looking for a loophole, it's definitely rooted in a wholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, you know, like, there was that...
[SPEAKER_03]: I was just talking with Tony the other day, and, you know, the rules for the monks evolved.
[SPEAKER_03]: They were not always 200 and 27.
[SPEAKER_03]: There was like 150 before or less.
[SPEAKER_03]: And there was the whole... the whole point was... they were kind of...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a product of circumstances and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: But they were the basic principles.
[SPEAKER_03]: The eight precepts, for example, are the basic principles.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that monk couldn't keep all hundred and fifty, whatever it was.
[SPEAKER_03]: It was before others had formulated.
[SPEAKER_03]: And he went to the Buddha and said, it's too much.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm going to disrobe because I can't keep all these rules.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then the Buddha said, well, you can just keep the three rules, don't do anything unwholesome by body, by speech, or by mind, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or then, on another occasion, when Mahāpajāpati went to ask the Buddha for a brief instruction before she goes for a little retreat, and so she can commit to the practice, and he said, whatever you know it's unwholesome, abandon it, whatever you know it's wholesome, don't recalculate it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that was enough for her to become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it comes down, all the way down, deep inside, to
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, you have to have enough mindfulness established to be recognizing thoughts as things, as phenomena that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, once you do, then, you can actually see.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, it's not... if you do see it at a level, it won't require that much... it's much harder to restrain.
[SPEAKER_03]: After your thoughts have been taken up, your level of the speech has been taken up, and now you're just kind of not quite doing unwholesome things with your body, so you're just enduring this build-up.
[SPEAKER_03]: But when you go back down to where your thoughts are, it's literally, it's just like with the stream, where the river just originates, when it's a tiny little stream.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then it doesn't require much effort to stop it, but it does require discernment to spot it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you go to the origin, you say, that is where you can see that you are responsible.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's when you see that you are the one making it wholesome or unwholesome, acting out of it, accepting unwholesome as an offer, ignoring wholesome as an offer.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in the beginning, you have to kind of start by, like, you know, crude restraint, just not doing, not looking, not saying, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's like... that's far from being a goal in itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: You do all of that just to eventually, through practice of mindfulness and reading the suttas and developing understanding of the dhamma, you can start distinguishing these things in your... like your thoughts already rooted in it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if at that level you address and literally just abstain from unwholesome on the level of the thoughts, that's... that's already like a... like a straight path in itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that really does mean, throughout the day, you have to be mindful of your thoughts, and then, when you recognize it, unwholesome thoughts, just, you don't tolerate.
[SPEAKER_03]: Doesn't mean you, ah, shouldn't be feeling like this, or you, I should, oh, these thoughts are wrong, I was, I was, ah, it was a big mistake.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have nothing to do with their arising.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thoughts arise and cease.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to, a lot to do with, exactly, with their accepting.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you accept the pleasing ones.
[SPEAKER_03]: You accept the ones you don't... you don't accept the ones you don't want.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then you change the criteria.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you reach to that level...
[SPEAKER_03]: You change the criteria.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's not anymore what I want, what I don't want.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's what I know it's wholesome, and what I know it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, whatever it's unwholesome, you you don't want it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the Buddha said, he... the Diljama, he doesn't entertain such thoughts, he doesn't indulge in them, he doesn't welcome them, he doesn't wish for them, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means, they might have a reason, but by him not entertaining them in any shape or form, they cease.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, no engagement with unwholesome has taken place.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if no engagement of unwholesome takes place at that very deep root level, well, it's certainly nothing can kind of, of the same kind, happen further down the stream.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because the stream hasn't been polluted in its origin.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means, even at the very end, it will be still the clean, wholesome stream.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, and that pertains to any type of thoughts, whether it's any type of unwholesome thoughts, whether it's a sensual thought, thought of ill will and anger, malice, thought of delusion, like just thoughts that are kind of revolving around indolence, laziness, indulgence of any kind.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know that those are unwholesome thoughts and you accept them.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's how the five hindrances work as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: They arise on their own.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're like almost manifestations of, you know, having a body.
[SPEAKER_03]: The body gets tired, the body gets excited, the body gets agitated and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you entertaining that... What was that?
[SPEAKER_03]: What was that?
[SPEAKER_03]: That's... That's a double-winged moth.
[SPEAKER_03]: It sounds like a double-winged plane as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, basically, by... the five hindrances, by not entertaining them, they cease to be hindrances.
[SPEAKER_03]: They cease to be obstacles.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the mind rises above them.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what's bothering me, by entertaining it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just that...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, you are.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're everybody.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's certain in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_02]: I do...
[SPEAKER_02]: I do... at times I would like force myself not to pursue it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I further carry on with it, like, you know, whatever, I've been thinking, thinking, and then I'm like, at one point, I'm not, I'm not carrying forward, this forward, and, you know, it takes some effort, but I do it, and I feel a bit pleased, like, you know, a bit happy or whatever, but, um, and I see that I have to keep doing it, and, um, you know, um, but it's just a fact.
[SPEAKER_02]: My day is spent just on that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just struggle that, like, either pursuing it or struggling with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, I'm not doing practically anything else.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, well, that's, that's basically the environment you live in.
[SPEAKER_03]: That, you know, the common household with exposure to, you know, pretty much any sensual aspect you want, whether it's food, music, entertainment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to... yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: You need to re-evaluate, see how serious you are, and then you have to change it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to take that leap, that step, and then change it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And by change it, I mean you go to the environment that doesn't support such an easy access to those things.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's a risky step, obviously, but then again, like, yeah, you can choose to stay, and then what?
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not going to live forever.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what, you're just going to be tipping and indulging every every whim that arises and giving completely in?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you just sort of hate yourself, and the day before that, and the day before that, you don't do anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: I see myself developing, in a way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, as you said, like, the rest of the sensual stuff, I'm doing pretty decent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, even the food-wise, at times, I see, like, I'm trying to, you know, trying to enjoy, and I, like, I take a step back, you know, and, like, music and the other really entertain, and, you know, all the other sensual stuff, I'm handling well.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, the problem is, you will... if you're waiting for yourself to feel like, oh, I am ready now, they'll never come.
[SPEAKER_02]: Actually, the thing I'm really afraid is that going like... because this is probably like my... if I'm going to Australia, that's probably my only opportunity.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, I can't invest again.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't have the money.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I know.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was in a very, very, very similar position.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, I had one shot at it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't want to, like, go there and I see, you know, if I see some, you know, women come,
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, all that, all that, all that is a real risk.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's just something you have to, well, you have to accept, really, and then face it, exactly, and then be stronger than it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because if you wait, oh, I'm just waiting for the circumstances to be right, for me to feel ready to go, it'll never happen.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, you know, your whole mind is taken by Māra.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means, it'll never make you ready for it.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's always going to be something.
[SPEAKER_03]: And often, you have...
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, I've seen so many people come into monasteries over the years, and they always kind of come and sort of are looking for a place.
[SPEAKER_03]: But they have the attitude of... they're looking for a perfect place.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're looking for a place that will do the practice for them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means, they'll never find that place.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means, they'll never actually start the practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: And they know that.
[SPEAKER_03]: You kind of, by putting the responsibility for the practice onto circumstances, be it a place, or if everything falls in place, I can really go and do it, or whatever else, you'll never do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It will never be perfect.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because your judgment of perfection is actually skewed.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what you're waiting to be perfect can never happen, because
[SPEAKER_03]: If it will happen, means the Mahārāja would encourage you to practice, and that will never happen.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mahārāja will never encourage you to go against him.
[SPEAKER_03]: He will always make it hard whenever you choose to go against the stream, which is why it's referred to as against the stream.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that against the stream starts from the very first step.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you might be inspired about it, you might have determination to do it, but it will never be, oh, yes, I'm going with the grain now, and I'm practicing.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: It always has to be against it, which is why it's risky.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not a guaranteed success.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you don't really know, when you do make that step, whether you made it too soon, or whether, you know, am I too late, or is it just...
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, at the same time, well,
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't really know what too soon is.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't really know what too late is.
[SPEAKER_03]: One thing you know is, it's going to be hard.
[SPEAKER_03]: And one thing you know is, well, you can always prevail.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you fail, it's not because it was too soon.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not because it was too late.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's because you failed.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's because you didn't prevail.
[SPEAKER_03]: It overwhelmed you.
[SPEAKER_03]: You didn't overwhelm it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: The defilement.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you know enough.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not, like, not specifically, like, one knows enough.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have the idea about the monastic life, what it entails, what the precepts are, where the practice is to be found, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there might be doubts or whatever else, but all that comes from those hindrances I was just talking about.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it all boils down whether you succeed or not in the end.
[SPEAKER_03]: And for that, you are solely responsible.
[SPEAKER_03]: For as long as your senses, your faculties are intact, you still have your life and so on, means there's absolutely no reason to not succeed.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you don't succeed, then, yeah, you'll have this reason or that reason, too soon, too late, and this and that.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you succeed, none of it matters.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because none of it mattered to begin with.
[SPEAKER_03]: If the practice was truly depending upon circumstances, well, it would be done.
[SPEAKER_03]: You wouldn't be able to do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, unless your faculties are impaired, anything like that happens, then, yeah, there's nothing really stopping you from doing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just whether you're strong enough or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: I see a lot of similarities with any sort of like intoxicant.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, I see myself trying to stop.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, I don't really do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, actually, the nature of addiction is well within the nature of sensuality in general.
[SPEAKER_03]: Addiction is just a particular manifestation of the nature of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Any addiction is just a more concentrated manifestation of what actually nature of sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, like, I see myself, like, wanting one last hit, one last time, and when I get it, I want more.
[SPEAKER_02]: And...
[SPEAKER_02]: I see what you mean, like, unless I take the step, it doesn't really... then it's gonna change.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, you might, like, oh, just one last hit of whatever was providing me with a hit, and then I'll do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that was already, like, flawed attitude to begin with.
[SPEAKER_02]: That hit is something that I want, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Once you get it, well, now there is a prospect of another last hit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because this was not last anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: It was last before you've done it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Once you've done it, well, now there's a possibility of another hit, which is, oh, well, that will be the last then.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you never stop.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you realize, well, the only way to stop is to stop.
[SPEAKER_03]: The last hit won't stop you.
[SPEAKER_03]: The first hit.
[SPEAKER_03]: A hundred more.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: The way to stop is to stop.
[SPEAKER_03]: And not give importance whether it's a beginning of the hit, end of the hit, or middle of the hit.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: You stop, independent of the hit.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what I was just saying about circumstances.
[SPEAKER_03]: You stop regardless of the circumstances, whether it's
[SPEAKER_03]: Whether it feels, oh, I was just halfway through this or through that, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you have to go a bit above, I'd say.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to become... You have to take the reins, really, and do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because otherwise it's just riding you around.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't... you can't have someone who's, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: An Aryan or noble person, who is being led by his caretaker, ah, come, you know, he's not like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: An Aryan is a strong person.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has... he's not weak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so by...
[SPEAKER_00]: The beginning of the... You always have to do, you know, you have to go above things, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's why the Buddha was saying this, like, you know, whatever was to be obtained by the manly effort, manly exertion, I have a point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's got nothing to do with...
[SPEAKER_03]: There isn't a greater manly effort than going against, you know, yourself, really.
[SPEAKER_03]: Going against the entire grain and then overpowering it.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's another sutra where the Buddha says the mind of the arahant,
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't overwhelm him.
[SPEAKER_03]: He overwhelms his mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, whatever arises in the mind, he's stronger than it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, that strength can't come through this force.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's going against it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It comes through, like, direct discernment, full insight, which overpowers anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what about like faith in like the beginning, you mean?
[SPEAKER_03]: Faith is necessary in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, not...
[SPEAKER_00]: Faith is not a goal in itself, as it is in Christianity and many other religions.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just faith that, ah, there is hope, that if I make the effort, I can be free.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I have faith in that.
[SPEAKER_03]: I have faith that my efforts are leading me the right way.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, when you know for a fact
[SPEAKER_03]: When your efforts are confirmed, when you know that you are on the right way, then the faith is automatically... well, faith disappears.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you don't need to believe that you're on the right way when you know that you're on the right way.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, confidence of knowledge replaces the faith.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the suttas refer to it as confirmed confidence, which Sotāpanna gets and then develops further and further and further.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, and he just went for the light.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is a big thing, that thing, eh?
[SPEAKER_00]: He just took that piece of room.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, smashed it into your face or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, ultimately, ultimately, for an ārahant, I mean, you know, he has no faith anymore, because he became fully developed in regard to dhamma and the practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: He completely went against the grain and now he can't.
[SPEAKER_03]: He just can't be overwhelmed, in a sense.
[SPEAKER_03]: He can't be brought back with the grain anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: He can't be fooled that way.
[SPEAKER_03]: He just went beyond.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like the Noble Eightfold Path,
[SPEAKER_03]: Goes against the grain.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, for an arahant, it's, eh... he goes beyond the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, grain against the grain, and then there is completely going over it, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't get back.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do... some of... like I asked, eh... myself, at least...
[SPEAKER_00]: I was... with sensual... with sensual thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I've asked myself, in fact, do I...
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I want... do I want to actually get beyond those things?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I really want to go beyond that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I want to be free from sensuality?
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you ask, yeah... Well, there's a good reflection and a reminder, you know, on a daily basis.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, as I was just saying, any form of sensuality and wholesome is being entertained, which is why it's present.
[SPEAKER_03]: It arises on its own.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, if you're feeling a central pull of any kind, or pull of ill will or anger, means, ah, you have already accepted it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're already entertaining it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then the reminder, well, hold on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do I want to go beyond this?
[SPEAKER_03]: Genuinely?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, well, then, entertaining it becomes more obvious.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, you kind of won't do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, you know, the more you do it, the more
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, the more you refrain from entertaining, the more... the more of practicing that insight, then you become more proficient at it, and it gets easier.
[SPEAKER_03]: But in the beginning, yeah, it's just like really enduring it, when it arises, and then trying to make the most of it, when it's not present.
[SPEAKER_03]: Most of it in terms of practice, I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh... You're like, what has... what has sensuality ever done for you, Kamal?
[SPEAKER_00]: It drove you around.
[SPEAKER_03]: Aimlessly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you've had it before.
[SPEAKER_00]: What more can... what more is it going to do, you know?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it going to achieve?
[SPEAKER_00]: We were just talking about it a few minutes, I think, before we started this recording.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, any form of sensuality of any sense, kind of, has its combination.
[SPEAKER_03]: Taste, sound, touch.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you realize, it's never going to be more than that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what then differs is just like having different ways of arriving at that culmination.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like different ways of obtaining taste, different ways of obtaining touch, different ways of obtaining sounds, smells and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's just like it becomes an indulgent anticipation of something that you've been through many times before.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, that's why you need to... like people kind of become really like connoisseurs of... are really taking it slowly, slowly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because if you just arrive at the end of it, it says, oh, that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you have to build up that anticipation, that delight.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Delighting in the prospect.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's why lots of people spend lots of time
[SPEAKER_03]: Masking and developing various elaborate ways of arriving at something plain and simple.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just a combination of the pleasure of any particular sense.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's all.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you approach it like that, then it's quite flat.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you have to refrain from that entertainment, from delighting in the prospect of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Entertaining you, you know, teasing it, leaving it for longer, so then you can kind of have greater pleasure.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, again, the nature of that pleasure, inherently, will always remain the same and can never be anything more than that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, you know, obviously, the extent people go for essential pleasure is just having family and children and everything.
[SPEAKER_03]: It all comes as a result of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And those are serious commitments, serious actions that affect other people.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it also says, oh, I want kids, I want this, I want family, I want people next to me, I want companions, whatever else.
[SPEAKER_03]: And as a form of just kind of getting to that pleasure, you commit to all sorts of things, to great extents.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then when you get it, then you realize, well, now you're too deep in to just leave it all out.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: On account of sensuality, you just went too far.
[SPEAKER_03]: You omitted, took too much on, the burden is too heavy, and you can't turn away from it anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, even then, it's not impossible.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, it's easier when you don't have many things pulling you back, in terms of responsibilities.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, say, even if you're a king or the ruler of the entire country, with wives and kids or whatever else, again, nothing stops you.
[SPEAKER_03]: From a decision made in a moment to just leave it all behind, as the Buddha did.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let alone if you, you know, if you have much less of responsibilities and opportunities as he did, or people like him.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like becoming an anticipator.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like being professional anticipating things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's basically what runs people's lives, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Anticipation, which is, you know, delight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like you delight at the future prospect.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, I'm gonna, like, I'm about to have this, I'm gonna have it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That anticipation, like always having something in stores.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's how people live their entire lives.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whether in terms of relationships, whether in terms of, you know, family, career, ambition, achievements, money, obviously, like, oh, anticipation, I'm making, I made some money, I'm earning, studying, learning, I'm like...
[SPEAKER_03]: Just all of those things are forms of anticipation.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you just stop and think, you realize, well, there is never an arrival to anything.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that anticipation is actually almost a goal in itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: That delight is what sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_03]: That anticipation is the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not the pleasure that you get from it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's that pull and being shackled by that anticipation.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pleasure is just pleasure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fully pertains to the senses, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that anticipation is that, is something for which you're responsible.
[SPEAKER_03]: That you're entertaining, that you're engaging, and it's driving you around, completely.
[SPEAKER_03]: Desire and lust, in regard to things.
[SPEAKER_03]: The light, at the prospect of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what sensuality is, not the actual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Prem, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, what is the point?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you get from giving up sensuality?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, like, again, see, like that, like, oh, I want to have one last hit, because I'm giving it up forever.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how it feels in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you stop and think about it, you realize, well, while you're giving up forever, is the anticipation revolving around
[SPEAKER_03]: Chasing things up, this kind of hope and expectation.
[SPEAKER_03]: The actual pleasure that was always pertaining to the senses, remains on the level of senses, and you don't mind giving that up, because it was just that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's... the fear arises when... because people are dependent upon anticipation and having this kind of something in store, like something waiting, something hopeful to happen.
[SPEAKER_03]: Giving that up fills you with dread, fills you with anxiety.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because like, oh, well, boredom.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's like nothing then.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just this.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just plain boredom.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is no pleasure here at all.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because for you, pleasure is the pleasure of anticipation.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that is the unwholesome pleasure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like craving for underlying tendencies, craving for more.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means, whenever there's anticipation, there will be more anticipation in regards to that.
[SPEAKER_03]: More delight, breathe more delight.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, only from the point of view of that, giving up pleasure feels like fearful, like fills you with fear.
[SPEAKER_03]: It seems like hope.
[SPEAKER_03]: But only in the beginning, yeah, because it feels like you're giving up hope.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you persevere for it, and not even that long, actually, you realize, well,
[SPEAKER_03]: The senses, they're ultimately the only thing that can experience this pleasure, are still there, whatever.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you don't really... like, they were not yours to begin with.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you don't fear giving up their pleasure, because they'll have something else.
[SPEAKER_03]: And they will have other types of pleasure that are not unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is why, when you start discerning those types of pleasure, you can... Well, that's how you abandon the unwholesome type.
[SPEAKER_03]: By developing wholesome pleasure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pleasure that it's not based on anticipation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pleasure of peace, pleasure of content, pleasure of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_03]: All of those are forms of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you can actually use them to abandon the unwholesome types of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need those pleasures at least.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, first you need to start the renunciation.
[SPEAKER_03]: You need to start to emulate it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you can start recognizing the pleasant aspect of it on account of which
[SPEAKER_03]: On account of that wholesome, pleasant aspect, you abandon the unwholesome, pleasant aspects, which are pleasures of anticipation, sensuality, delight, chasing after things, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the hope that that provides
[SPEAKER_00]: It seems like it's such a big challenge.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the biggest, it's the most difficult thing to do, to overcome sensuality, to overcome anticipation, overcome craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how many people can do that?
[SPEAKER_00]: How many people have done that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it takes so much strength to do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's far from impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, far from impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's only like... only a few people can do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think about it all, how many people there are currently on the planet.
[SPEAKER_00]: Billions of people and... And you'll be the only one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you're the only one or two people in the world actually making the efforts in that direction, in cleaning your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: The rest, they become...
[SPEAKER_03]: No, that's a very... that's like using vanity, using conceit to your advantage.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, I will be the only one free from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because of that, you will be making efforts to free yourself from sensuality, and then you can, and you will.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when you free yourself from sensuality, you won't feel, I am the, you know, the only one free.
[SPEAKER_03]: You won't care about it, because you're free from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that vanity, that conceit will vanish with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it did make you strive properly.
[SPEAKER_03]: And everybody can follow their desires.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's absolutely zero effort involved, which is why everybody does it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, again, you just have to stop and reflect for just a brief period of time and realize, well, yeah, sure, following desire... desires doesn't require any effort.
[SPEAKER_03]: But in order to have the availability for my desires,
[SPEAKER_03]: I need to put up with lots of stuff that I hate, that I don't want, that I want to be associated with, I don't want to have to do, but I do it just that I can have a moment where I can just let it go and just flow with the desire that has a reason and kind of, you know, relax.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then you spend 85-90% of your life just putting up with stuff you hate, you don't want,
[SPEAKER_03]: So that you can get that 5% satisfaction of just having it your own way and satisfying this particular desire or that particular desire.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, people work the entire week hard, so they can completely, you know, sprint and go mad over the weekend.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's their whole life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Be the master of your weekend.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, it's just like the course is all kind of example, but basically, in principle, that's the Putujana's ley line.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like putting up with stuff, why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you want a family, you want a wife, you want the children.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, now I have to support it, now I have to work for it, now I have to endure lots of stuff you hate, because you committed to this.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you sort of, you can, again, without much reflection or effort, recognize, well, with a little bit of effort, with 5% of effort,
[SPEAKER_03]: I can have 95% of my time not putting up with stuff I hate, actually being quite free.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why the Buddha compared, like, life of a samana, and especially if somebody will develop wisdom and insight, like, free as a deer, roaming as a deer, just go wherever you please, whenever you please, you are your own master.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, it's the... it's basically what everybody dreams of.
[SPEAKER_03]: But because being too weak in regard to their own desires, they end up making compromises, they end up being the burden that weighs down on them, and then you're stuck.
[SPEAKER_03]: It crushes you, doesn't it, Chief?
[SPEAKER_01]: In the beginning, you overcome the defilement.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you overcome the fear of a defilement?
[SPEAKER_03]: To overcome the defilement, how do you overcome the fear of the defilement?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, for example, the, I mean, sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you fear how, you know, the sensuality gets over, I mean, sort of like... Well, you don't have to overcome.
[SPEAKER_03]: You use that fear to not engage with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: You develop it more.
[SPEAKER_03]: Until sensuality frightens you so much, that you do not give in.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's seeing the danger in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_03]: Seeing the threat in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_03]: Being afraid of the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then eventually, when you stop giving in to those faults, then that fear will fade.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because now you're confident that you will not give in, thus you have nothing to fear.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a rain here.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's good.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is a heavy rain.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Doesn't seem like a five-minute rain in Bambarella.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's good.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's dry, phone dry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's already raining like this now, and it's still dry, that's good.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the trees are not getting hit, eh?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no, it's not hitting you.
[SPEAKER_03]: You see this tree, nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thanks a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: I also think that authenticity is such a power, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you're authentic, the more authentic you are, the more powerful you become.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, literally, you become powerful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you know...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even for myself, I know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If sensuality comes, if the sexual desire comes up, I have the power to put it out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again... Because I'm the one doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm the one actually bringing it about.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't switch it off at any point.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you develop confidence in your own power, mental power,
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, you don't fear.
[SPEAKER_03]: And again, that's the simile from the suttas often compared to a lion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like the lion, the king of the jungle.
[SPEAKER_03]: He doesn't fear any other roars that he hears, that arise.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because he is the king of the jungle.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's his roar that others fear.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, when he sleeps there, somebody roars, some other animals make noise, he doesn't even flinch.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because he knows nobody's coming out.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nobody can come after him.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's when the mind develops any sensuality, any ill will, anything that arises like on its own, you don't fear it, because you know, ah, it won't overwhelm me, I'll overwhelm that, if it comes here.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it doesn't come there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Say, you have been burning in the fire now,
[SPEAKER_01]: Say, you have been entertaining the defilement for so long, and you have been entertaining that particular defilement, I mean, quite dedicated to the defilement.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there has to be a gradual, sort of like,
[SPEAKER_01]: You say, coming off that defilement.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, I mean, as I said, you stop things when you stop them.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not kind of waning off it, waiting for it to kind of fade out and stop, and do the stopping for you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah, the longer you've been entertaining a particular habit of unwholesome time, it will be harder to give it up.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you give it up when you give it up.
[SPEAKER_03]: You stop doing it and then you just endure and you have to withstand any pull.
[SPEAKER_03]: And those pulls can't last forever.
[SPEAKER_03]: They won't last forever.
[SPEAKER_03]: They will last for as long as
[SPEAKER_03]: So, all you have to do is remain undeterred.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the Buddha was dying, Ananda asked the Buddha, he says, what should we do in regards to women?
[SPEAKER_00]: How should we... and he says... Don't look at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, don't look at them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, yeah... What do you have to look at it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't speak with them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why don't you speak with them?
[SPEAKER_03]: Then you can fortify your mind and be mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I was interested in there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, be mindful, but it seems to me at different stages, because...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why would you want to be mindful, if you can avoid it in the first place?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, why would you want to have to be mindful in regards to it, when dealing... because, basically, mindful... you have to be mindful, because that's the way to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why would you wait for that long in order to have to deal with it when you can prevent it from arising in the first place?
[SPEAKER_03]: Don't look at it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Don't speak with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then be mindful if you have to do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that was like basically in regards to... that question was asked women in a sense of sensuality for men.
[SPEAKER_03]: What should you do?
[SPEAKER_03]: How you should deal with it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, your discernment, it's not about testing yourself or seeing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: You see it, you cut it and it's you.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't engage at the level of sight.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't engage at the level of speaking.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you can't avoid that, well, then you'll be mindful as the last resort in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because actually, being able to prevent it, that's already implying mindfulness at the proper time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Having wisdom to discern it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ah, I could prevent this, cut my work in half.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the thing, when the Buddha is saying, be mindful, he's not... he's talking about right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's also someone who knows what that is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've got to know.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't...
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't do right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I have to avoid these things for the time... well, for the time being.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that result of overcoming this thing, it's still not available.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you want to basically kind of exclude it then, as an option.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's in the Hindu tradition, you know, they do seven years of celibacy.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you don't look at a woman, you don't speak to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've got nothing to do with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just to maintain your celibate life, so you can build up this energy and attain some higher state.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that better?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it does... you have to go through this.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to hold that and not be around those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can actually have a better, a firmer grip on your mind, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, by not being, by not engaging in those things on the level of sight, speech, touch, whatever else, then your mind can, right, well, encompass it fully as a phenomenon of sensuality, attraction, desire, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: By not being engaged, because the moment you're engaged with it, well, then, already, mind is in it, which means it will be seeing it from a different angle that's within that, which means you can't then be possibly seeing correctly how it is to be outside of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you need to actually be outside in order to recognize that you're outside.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can be inside and then you fantasize how it is to be outside, but that's that's not the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, and again, the simile in the suttas is,
[SPEAKER_03]: Like being in the water, wet, having two wet pieces of wood, trying to light the fire by rubbing them together.
[SPEAKER_03]: It won't work.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you step outside on the shore, but then you have to wait until that wood dries out, and then you can you can start a fire, like light the spark of wisdom and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah, you might have stopped engaging in sensuality, but then you have to
[SPEAKER_03]: Maintain that for a while, until the mind dries up, and then it can discern and see clearly for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you go, you take the pieces of wood out of the water, but they're drying up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Helps you to see more subtle things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you see your thoughts, the origin of these things.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's basically like being wet means your mind is wet, your thoughts are wet.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that means, it's like, it sort of dampens.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is no, there can't be like a fire of wisdom, energy of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_03]: It can't arise, because everything is wet, soggy wet.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you need to stop making it wet, and then you have to, by not making it wet, you have to persevere in that, until it dries out completely, and then things will become more evident.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think one of the things that's become evident, I would say, well, is that sutta when the Buddha talks about giving attention to your masculine features, masculine entity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I find myself, if I'm not thinking central thoughts, I'm not entertaining it as much as I can, you know, I don't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when I delight
[SPEAKER_00]: In my masculinity, in my body, I can see it coming, pushing, or giving that, how do you say, pressure, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, funny you said that, but I had the same, same, same issues.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, but what I found, what I, what I practiced with is, if I do notice that,
[SPEAKER_00]: If I... then I can also either give attention to my masculine feature, where I feel, like, powerful in my muscles or whatever, or I don't...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can feel strong, but I don't have to delight in that, you know, in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a... but you need to be dry enough to be able to see that as well, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can see that, but I think things have to be a bit drier to see the subtler.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, the drier you are,
[SPEAKER_03]: As I said, the more things you begin to discern, more and more and more, things that you could have seen because it was all wet.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see where the enemy comes in.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you come to that point, then all you have to do is never give attention to masculine side, which means there will never be an opening.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: For the attraction in regard to the opposite to arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't mean that you become, eh, non-masculine.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, not at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, in fact, it's what we just spoke, what I was saying, you become very strong.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's also not a vanity strength, pride strength, strength based on the physical appearance and whatever else.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the strength of the mind, which is a different, very different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But yeah, it's a valid strength.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it's THE real strength.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I want to know, to be honest about what exactly, eh, you sound like I'm going to have, eh, since that, as you said, like, I have, I've, I'm in the best kind of physical condition I've been in years.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, ah, such a waste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I'm in my prime or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, sometimes I find myself laughing at
[SPEAKER_01]: How funny, like, the different ways that the mind approaches the same thing to get it done, like, when it comes to defilement.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are, like, different, different approaches.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, like, at times, when I notice, like, how, eh... how do you call it, like, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not complex, but how, how, how... while the time, you know, the way the mind approaches the same refinement, it's just, you know, it's very laughable.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, well, that's exactly how, how Māra works, really.
[SPEAKER_03]: And all you have to do is just ignore it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just don't, don't give a full attention to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, yeah, it will follow its course.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it will take you with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just turn a blind eye, here and there.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ignore.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ignoring.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's heavy rain.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not making it easier.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that is some heavy rain, man.
[SPEAKER_01]: I started feeling that, you know, I started feeling like, oh, I feel like going on fire with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then again, I realized that it's one of those, one of the ways I'm trying to avoid
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah,
[SPEAKER_00]: What happens is that just you feel... you don't want to... you just want to avoid things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to go to sleep, rather.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, yeah, that's why the sloth and tortle become a... become a hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you see... you see actually how much... you don't need sleep.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can actually sleep very little.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the rest of the time, it's just...
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to just be ignored.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't want to actually watch my thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't want to look at things.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's quite painful, I think.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it can be.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's because having ways in you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, kind of.
[SPEAKER_03]: But again, the thing is, with every hindrance, it's actually rooted in the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, same.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the body does need sleep.
[SPEAKER_03]: The body does get sleepy.
[SPEAKER_03]: The body does get agitated.
[SPEAKER_03]: The body does get excited.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, any sensuality experience, it's completely confined to the body and bodily senses.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can, by discerning fully, that the extent of, of, uh, nivāraṇa, the hindrance, is fully bound with the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: We can actually surmount it like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: It can never spill over.
[SPEAKER_03]: It can never be anything more than bodily.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, all you have to do is not give in to your body and you don't give in to any hindrance.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what about with that?
[SPEAKER_03]: How is that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, even the doubt, that doubt, like, it's the form of the doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you are actually affected by the doubt, it's felt.
[SPEAKER_03]: You experience it in your body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, when the doubt takes over you, when you're panicking on account of doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when you're nillinious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is simple.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the two ways.
[SPEAKER_03]: And also, it doesn't...
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not saying that the five images are physical, in terms of they're found in your body, like whatever else.
[SPEAKER_03]: It means they pertain to your body.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what it is, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It means they pertain to your body.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're bodily.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're bound with the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: They cannot be experienced without the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're saying then, when you recognize a point in time, you should recognize it as arising while the body is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But do you recognize it while the body is there?
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what it means, bound with the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: It means, to the extent the body is, they are.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you're not...
[SPEAKER_03]: They can't be found elsewhere, independently of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the domain, the domain of the five hindrances is always there in regard to the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically, it means the domain is maintained through the... if you're not free from possibility of accepting any of the hindrances that arises on account of body.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when you accept it, when you give in to it, when you're affected by it, all of that, that's when it's a hindrance.
[SPEAKER_03]: If your mind becomes stronger, literally, just stronger than the hindrance...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it doesn't mean that you never experience sleepiness, or like the body never gets excited.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the mind is always, on every occasion, stronger than any of those things.
[SPEAKER_03]: That means you are not taken by... you cannot be taken up by any hindrance anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then your mind is seeing it in the right view, with the right view.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, the right view will take you there, and then it's just developing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, there's... like, if you can see the hindrances,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can be mindful of your thoughts, but you also have to be able to see it, like they were saying, arising with the body... Yeah, you also have to be strong enough to endure the body, basically, with its pulls.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you... that means you have to have a right... the right view, like... Well, yes, but also, like, if you don't have the right view, it can certainly enable you to have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can we end like that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Can we end like that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it's along the right line.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you don't have the right view, you'll certainly develop one if you practice like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how does Vyāpāda put an end to your body?
[SPEAKER_00]: Anger.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, see, it pertains to your body internally, and pertains to the body just externally, or just to the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: For as long as a body is there, it will pertain to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, can you be angry with any person, without an image of their body, their appearance, their face, their tokens, their signs, anything physical?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if you say, well, I don't hate...
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not talking about hating the physical aspects.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can hate what somebody said.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can hate them on account of what they said.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you have that phenomenon of hate present, you have, simultaneously, that phenomenon is bound with the presence of their bodily image that you're encountering.
[SPEAKER_03]: The face or the entire... whatever.
[SPEAKER_03]: It will be pertaining to the bodily aspect.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is not accidental, then, that giving in to hate would result in you attacking the physical aspect.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whether through verbal abuse, if you have even less restraint, through physical abuse.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, annihilation, destruction of the physical aspect is the satisfaction of your anger.
[SPEAKER_03]: Same with desire, sexual desire, sexual desire, inseparable from bodily.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't have it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You either have to have an image of your body present, in a form of giving in to the notion of your own masculinity, or you have the image of external body's presence, or both.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, the wind is better than this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe that.
[SPEAKER_00]: What I just noticed, before I left, I was at Kingo, looking at the sūtra.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a sūtra on watching two types of thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by discerning wholesome thought and unwholesome thought,
[SPEAKER_00]: Eventually, he answers the first time and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But also, by discerning the five hindrances, he... then he answers first time.
[SPEAKER_00]: The same... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The same question.
[SPEAKER_03]: These five hindrances are basically five ways the unwholesome thought can manifest itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nowhere apart from them, it can be unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, by recognizing the domain of the five hindrances, you... you sort of overcome the domain of unwholesome manifestation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I like.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... it's just so... it's just a simple thing, it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a good, excellent thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know?
[SPEAKER_03]: Depending how far you pursue it, how clearly you discern it,
[SPEAKER_03]: That will determine how far you get.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it is pressure-wise.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is pretty difficult.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it's like climbing up, high up on the hill.
[SPEAKER_03]: The higher you get, the more pressure there is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It gets harder, whatever else, but then, yeah, there is a reward for it eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's always the possibility of the pleasure... Of falling down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But going back to the pleasure that you know.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you keep going, there will be a point of no return.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you know, ah, you cannot return, you will not return.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's impossible for you to return.
[SPEAKER_03]: To the pleasure that you know.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, as the sutra say, like the stone that has been split in half, you can never ever make it one again.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or like a dry leaf that came off the tree, it can never be green again.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or even like, you know, slightly more vivid examples of like food you vomited out, you cannot desire it again.